just copy and paste this so let's say X
hey everyone welcome to video 1 in a
part three series of punctures praça dos
and monads in Haskell this video will be
honourable functors so let's begin I'm
just gonna start off by writing the
definition here and then we're gonna
work our three way through it and don't
make sense by the end so firstly a
functor is a type class now what is the
type class a type class you can think of
it as an interface it's not really an
interface but you can think of it as an
interface so what that means is that the
function is a type class and it defines
or it gives us the signature for a
method and we have to implement that
method on our own so this is what it
looks like in Haskell so we're gonna do
class functor F where F map F map is the
function that it gives us the signature
for to be F a FB so this is exactly what
it looks like and I'm gonna explain how
this works so in Haskell we have
something called a rapid value and we
have something called an unwrapped value
what is it wrap to value
well sorry what is it unwrapped I unwrap
values basically just a value on its own
for example let's say I had +3 applied
to something like 9 the 9 here is an
unwrapped value because it's not
surrounded by anything a wrapped value
is something that is surrounded by
something the obvious case here is an
example that might come to your head is
in maybe so in asked what we have this
maybe object which is basically just a
or nothing right so in this case what we
have what's if I do just eight we
consider or we say that 8 is a wrapped
and adjust and I think this photo here
illustrates the best that we have an a
inside and then it wrapped around it's
wrapped around by something if I wanted
to apply a function to this just
eight how would I do it I can't do this
can I
it won't work I can do +3 9 to unwrapped
value but to a rapid value it doesn't
matter what to a rapt value it does not
work and that's where the functor comes
into play a functor essentially what it
does it takes in a function so here's
how we will call it will call f map will
call some sort of functions LS c plus 3
and we'd pass in our f of a so maybe
this is like a wrapped value and then
what it should give us in the end
it's just seven so it gives us the
wrapped are you back where the function
here has been applied to this internal
variable so let's exactly see how we're
gonna make that happen in maybe so I'm
gonna define maybe two here I tend to
cut two maybe
and as you can see so I'm just to eight
and obviously have to derive show in
order for it to show so I did just to
eight as you can see it's here I'm gonna
apply this functor to maybe two how I'm
gonna do that is I'm gonna write
instance functor maybe to where so
remember we have to code this F map
function which is what has God finds f
MA now we have to call the two cases so
function just to a is equal to and F
function
nothing is equal if wondering why is
this function here well this is a
function right over here a to be this
just a is our f of a I'm not gonna
return an F of B well the easy case here
is that if I pass in nothing or if I'm
getting in nothing then regardless of
the function I apply I should get back
nothing that makes sense if I have a
chest and I'm trying a function then I
want to apply the function to the
internal value which is a and then I
want to wrap it around in a just
so this is how it is this is how easy it
works for which to do it again now let
me do something like Earth Map the
function here is plus three and gonna do
just two eight now you're gonna see it
gives me just 211 and something about
Haskell is that it already defines it
for a bunch of stuff a bunch of data
types it already defines the functor
method for example the regular just it's
already defined as if I was to do just
eight it's already defined right over
there it's also defined in list it's
also defined in either so in a list that
actually becomes very easy because in a
list if I was to do Earth Map we do plus
three one two three
well we have four five six the reason
here is that F map in the list is
actually equal to just map right because
if I was to do map plus three one two
three
I would get back the same exact thing so
that's what a functor is a functor
basically what it does is it applies a
function to a wrapped value and gives us
a raptor value back so functors when
you're gonna be using them they're gonna
be there it's gonna be very tedious to
keep earning f map f map every time so
high school offers an infix notation
infix basically means in between and
essentially what you do is we have a
function then it's the angle brace the
dollar sign and go brace again and then
the item or the wrapped value and then
we're gonna get the same thing back so
this this thing here it's identical to
same f map plus three just do for it I
tend to go to saying that it's just in
Haskell it's easier if you have an infix
notation just like this so we know that
Haskell offers the functors for maybe
either list and a bunch of other stuff
but most of the time you want to apply
functors to your own programs or your
own data structures so the most common
example is a tree and the tree how we're
going to define it is the following way
so just gonna have data tree
is equal to so it's gonna have a chip
and it's gonna be a branch so in branch
we'll have 3a and tree so I'll show you
an example of what this might look like
something like this so here's a tree the
4 5 & 6 are tips and these individual
things right over here are the branches
so this would be something with this
branch tip 4 and then branch tip 5 and
then tip 6 this is what it will look
like when you apply F map to it we apply
it at the tips and this is our resultant
tree so this is an example that it's not
implemented by Haskell and we're gonna
implement it right now so again we do
the same way so we do instance function
tree where again we have two cases so we
have F map function we're gonna have a
tip a I'm gonna have map function I'm
gonna have branch left and then right
what the tip a is easy because all we
need to do here is apply the function so
functionally and surrounded by a tip the
branch so the branch is different
because again we still need to
surrounded by a branch as per the type
construct but what will be the two
things are over here well we know that
in a branch if it's a left and if it's a
right we can't apply the function we
can't apply F map just yet because it
needs to go all the way down to a tip so
what we're gonna do is we're gonna
recurse and now we're going to recurse
is f map F left and F map F rights and
we could have again wrote F map F right
as F infix operator right just to save
space but I think it's much clearer this
way so this is a pattern you're gonna
see when you're at your most basic case
you just apply the function otherwise
you can ever curse so that's this let's
just take a look at it with a bunch of
errors
F this should be function function
rights and there should work so let me
just put deriving show here so I can
show you an example and she I'll just
is equal to the following so X is equal
to following that's clear and then what
I want to do is I want to apply a flap
let's do plus 3/2 X and as you can see
it works properly originally X was this
and it has applied 3 to each and every
one of them so know this video was kind
of long but it was basically just to lay
out what a functor is and how we're
gonna use it so we showed an example of
where it's already used and then created
our own example to show how we can use
it in our own programs I hope you
enjoyed this video and if you have any
questions please leave them in the
comments otherwise I'll see you in the
next video thank you